Okay בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's דף daf is דף ט. daf
tet. We start on the new
משנה, mishnah, top of ט עמוד א. tet amud aleph. It's a
slightly peculiar משנה mishnah as you'll see.
And well, let's just jump in and take a look. Okay, so
כנדרי רשעים. knidrei reshaim. If somebody says—this is understood to be an
issue about ידות, yadot, a continuation of the יד yad discussion. If
somebody says that this should be forbidden to me like the נדרים
nedarim of the—like or this should be on me. We'll see exactly
what they said. But they said some type of a statement like
that would be a נדר neder or a נזירות. nezirus. We'll see
in a minute. And they said like the נדרים nedarim of the
wicked. So נדר בנזיר ובקרבן ובשבועה. nadar binazir u-vekorban u-vishvuah. So that
person would have vowed regarding נזיר, nazir, קרבן, korban, and שבועה. shvuah.
Now what does that mean? So basically, the way the גמרא gemara
says it is let's say somebody says כנדרי רשעים הריני. knidrei reshaim
hareni. Like the vows of רשעים reshaim behold I am, or אהא,
ahei, I will be. And somehow we're supposed to understand that you
fill in the blank like אהא נזיר. ahei nazir. Or כנדרי רשעים,
knidrei reshaim, you know, הרי זו. harei zo. Like the vows of
רשעים reshaim this should be a קרבן. korban. Or כנדרי רשעים, knidrei
reshaim, you know, I won't do this following thing. So like a
שבועה shvuah that I won't.
So is שבועה shvuah a נדר?
neder? Well, no, well, okay yes, that's true too. But we'll worry
about that in a minute. So there's two parts to this. Meaning
one is that you don't spell out the end of your sentence.
One is that you say I will be and you don't say
I'll be a נזיר. nazir. You don't say this will be a
קרבן korban or the obligation of a קרבן korban is on me.
Or you don't say a שבועה shvuah that I won't do the
following things that you don't have one of the keywords and that
would be a standard יד. yad. And then the question is always
going to be how do we know how we're supposed to fill
in the blank. Is it a יד מוכיח, yad moche'ach, a יד
אינו מוכיח? yad einu moche'ach? If it's a יד אינו מוכיח, yad
einu moche'ach, then does it work at all? And even if it
does work, how do we know what you intended? That's like one
whole collection of things. But the חידוש chiddush of the משנה mishnah
seems to be the first phrase, the כנדרי רשעים. knidrei reshaim. And
what are you supposed to mean by that? And what's going to
be clear when we read the end of the משנה mishnah is
that if you say כנדרי רשעים, knidrei reshaim, then it works. Okay,
however, let's focus on that. That's really the חידוש chiddush of the
משנה. mishnah. כנדרי רשעים knidrei reshaim works. כנדרי כשרים לא אמר כלום.
knidrei kisherim lo amar klum. Like the נדרים nedarim of כשרים kisherim
people, you didn't say anything.
כשרים kisherim people don't make נדרים.
nedarim. That's exactly the point.
כנדבתם, knidvoson, however, if you say like the נדבה nidva of כשרים,
kisherim, then that does work.
נדר בנזיר ובקרבן. nadar binazir u-vekorban. It does work. Presumably כנדבות רשעים
knidvos reshaim would not work. The other thing that's missing from the
end of this משנה mishnah is שבועה. shvuah. It doesn't say נדר
בנזיר ובקרבן ובשבועה. nadar binazir u-vekorban u-vishvuah. So basically what the משנה
mishnah is telling us is two things. Number one is—and this will
be a nice opportunity for the גמרא gemara to get into at
least part of its discussion from time to time—it'll have a discussion
about the intrinsic religious value of making נדרים. nedarim. Is it a
good thing or a bad thing? So one of the things that
the גמרא gemara is going to get to is basically the message
here is that רשעים reshaim make נדרים nedarim and כשרים kisherim make
נדבות. nidvos. Okay? And not vice versa. Now what's the difference between
a נדר neder and a נדבה? nidva? And why do we say
that like רשעים—we reshaim don't mean that if somebody makes a נדר
neder they're objectively a רשע rasha in all of their doings, but
we basically mean that it is a—at least the way the ר"ן
Ran sort of says—בדבר זה. bedavar zeh. Like in this type of
an act, you know, when it comes to making נדרים nedarim and
נדבות, nidvos, it's a lesser act to make or you know it's
an inappropriate act to make a נדר. neder. So it doesn't mean
you're globally—right, well like that gets to the other question, נדרי מצווה
nidrei mitzvah is a different discussion, but we're going to bracket that.
But you know, now what's the diff—so anyway, but at least in
this particular local act, that would be a wrong thing to do,
so that's how it comes qualified as כנדרי רשעים. knidrei reshaim. Now
what's the difference? So קרבן korban is the easiest place to see
the difference. If you take a נדר neder of הרי עלי, harei
alai, I have an obligation to bring a קרבן. korban. That's a
classic נדר. neder. As a classic נדבה nidva is הרי זו, harei
zo, this is a קרבן. korban. So הרי עלי harei alai is
asking for trouble, right? Because הרי עלי harei alai means you have
this outstanding obligation and you might never get around to fulfilling it,
right? כי תדור נדר לה' אלהיך לא תאחר לשלמו. Ki tidor neder
l'Hashem Elokecha lo te'acher l'shalmo. Right, do not postpone doing it, right?
And it's you know, and it's טוב אשר לא תדור משתדור ולא
תשלם. tov asher lo tidor mi'shetiddor v'lo tishalem. פסוקים pesukim that the
גמרא gemara is going to quote in a minute. Better not to
take vows. Oh you think you're such a צדיק? tzaddik? You're going
to show how פרום frum you are, you're going to take a
vow, you know, it's not going to be worth it if you're
not going to be able to fulfill it. So that's why—well okay,
we will talk about that. Now how is the נדבה nidva better?
So that's for like a נדר neder is asking for trouble. How
is a נדבה nidva better? A נדבה nidva is you say הרי
זו, harei zo, this animal is a קרבן. korban. Now what that
means is you still have an issue of בל תאחר. bal te'acher.
If you don't wind up bringing this animal to the בית המקדש,
Beis HaMikdash, you're still going to be עובר over in בל. bal.
However, it's a little bit safer because if the animal gets lost
or dies or something of that nature, then you're done. You don't
have an obligation on your person, you've only sanctified the animal, so
if something happens to the animal, you have no longer any remaining
obligation. Of course, one could argue that there's also a greater danger.
The greater danger is if you have an עולה Olah sheep walking
around in your flock, you might come to misuse it. So it's
not so—but okay, but at least there the גמרא Gemara will say
there is at least a circumstance, I'm just now giving you a
summary of the whole גמרא, Gemara, but it's important to understand what's
going on in the משנה. Mishna. There's a circumstance where you can
make a נדבה Nedava pretty much be free from everything, which is
you walk your sheep to the בית המקדש Beis hamikdash and a
minute before you enter into the מקדש Mikdash you say הרי זו.
Harey zo. Of course, somebody could say you could walk your sheep
to the בית המקדש Beis hamikdash and a minute before you walk
in you say הרי עולה. Harey Olah. Anyway, somehow that's seen as
a נדבה Nedava is the more appropriate thing to do. Now, that's
all very lovely, but what does that have to do with the
idea of a נזיר? Nazir? How can you have a נדר Neder
or a נדבה Nedava as a נזיר? Nazir? נזיר Nazir basically making
yourself into a נזיר. Nazir. How can you have a נדר Neder
or a נדבה Nedava in a שבועה? Shvua? What would that even
mean? I mean, a שבועה Shvua is taking an oath. So the
ר"ן Ran basically says that there's not a sort of technical legal
difference between those. Those actually just reflect different sort of like circumstances
and motivations. That the word נדבה, Nedava, you know, when the תורה
Torah speaks about תרומה Terumah in פרשת תרומה—the Parshat Terumah ר"ן Ran
doesn't quote this, but he alludes to it—וכל נדיב לב אשר ידבנו
לבו. V'chol nediv lev asher yidvenu libo. So נדבה Nedava has a
sense of like the generosity of your heart. Okay, so a נדבה,
Nedava, says the ר"ן, Ran, refers to somebody that is doing this
because of sincere, you know, religious motivations. Just wants to serve God,
give something to God or whatever. That's like the idea of a
נדבה. Nedava. Whereas a נדר Neder might have some, you know, more
sort of like, you know, complicated sort of motivations. You know, I
you know, a lot of times people are doing things and they're
doing things to be פרום, frum, but there's other things going on
in their head too, right? You know, like, I don't know, you
feel angry at yourself, so you want to make a נדר Neder
or you feel, you know, you know, somehow, you know, you
become a נזיר Nazir because you're fed up with some, you know,
with certain types of behavior. Or look, maybe you even feel bad,
like you see that you've been sinning and you want to correct
it, so therefore you want to make a נדר Neder or a
נדבה. Nedava. So there's a religious component to it, but it's not
so much like just from the free-flowing, you know, uncomplicated, religious, you
know, sort of motivation. So that's more what he says in this
נדר Neder category. So it's a little bit tautologous, right, to say
that I'm say—I mean, not really, but to say like, you know,
נדרי רשעים, Nidrei rshaim, we're going to define the word as נדר
Neder to mean, you know, say things out of less, you know,
out of more complex, more complicated religious motivations. So that's what the
word like נדר Neder sort of symbolizes. Again, it's not a technical
legal difference. Okay, so if you say כנדרי כשרים לא אמר כלום,
Ke-nidrei kesherim lo amar klum, because a כשר kasher person doesn't say
things out of complicated religious motivations. They just freely say something, a
נדבה. Nedava. That's what כשרים kesherim do, it's not what רשעים rshaim
do.
Well, okay, so different ways you could be a נזיר. Nazir. You
could be a נזיר Nazir out of a נדר Neder motivation, which
is more complicated, and you could be a נזיר Nazir out of
a נדבה Nedava motivation. Okay, so again, it's interesting because then it
doesn't have a technical legal difference. It's a way of describing sort
of, you know, the religious mindset or motivation of the person making
it. And therefore by people that are again, why you call somebody
a רשע? rasha? Everybody has complicated motivations. Who has pure motivations? But
anyway, okay, but that's sort of the נדר Neder reflects a more
complicated sort of religious mindset, complex, whereas נדבה Nedava is just the
complete free, you know, free motivation, free will. And therefore if you
say נדרי רשעים Nidrei rshaim it's a meaningful statement.
נדבות רשעים Nidvos rshaim is not a meaningful statement. נדרי כשרים Nidrei
kesherim is not meaningful. נדבות כשרים Nidvos kesherim is because again it's
just describing where these people are coming from. Yes.
What's tripping me up a little bit is the formulation הרי עלי
Harey alay because הרי עלי, Harey alay, doesn't it imply הרי עלי
Harey alay to do something whereas נדר Neder was on the object...?
Yeah, so when it comes to a קרבן, Korban, that's what getting
back to the issues we discussed before about the whole idea of
a נדר Neder for צדקה tzedakah and so on, so when it
comes to a קרבן, Korban, then you can have a נדר Neder
which is a הרי עלי. Harey alay. Sort of the same way
we discussed that yesterday about a צדקה tzedakah נדר, Neder, right? Whereas
a classic נדרי איסור, nidrei issur, which is what our מסכת masechet
is, is הרי זו. Harey zo. In certain areas of נדרי מצוה,
nidrei mitzvah, particularly קרבן Korban and צדקה, tzedakah, it can create a
personal obligation and then it became the question of can you just
create a general נדר מצוה neder mitzvah like to obligate yourself to
learn a דף גמרא? daf Gemara? All right, so now, so let's
take a look at so if you want to see the line
in the רמב"ן Ramban ר"ן, Ran, take a look here. He says
like
this: And ואיכא דמדייק Ve-ika d'madik says the ר"ן Ran three lines
in the wide lines הרי נדבה אינה אלא באומר הרי זו Harei
nidavah eina ela b'omer harei zo ונדר זה האומר הרי עלי v'neder
ze ha'omer harei alai וחילוק זה לא שייך אלא בנדרים דקרבנות v'chiluk
ze lo shayach ela b'nedarim d'korbanos אבל בנזירות מאי נדר ומאי נדבה
שייך ביה aval b'nezirus mai neder u'mai nedavah shayach bei הרי אינו
אלא בעניין אחד harei eino ela b'inyan echad
there's one way to become a נזיר. nazir. ועוד בנזיר דנדר פירושו
דבר שאינו
בא לגמרי בנדבת הלב.
v'od b'nazir d'neder peirusho davar she'eino ba
l'gamrei b'nidvas halev. Okay, it doesn't come purely from totally from the
pureness of your heart and the free giving of your heart. ונדבה
פירושה u'nedavah peirusha sorry ונדבה פירושו מה שהאדם נודר יותר בנדבת נפשו
ושמעשיו יותר רצויים u'nedavah peirushu ma she'hadam noder yoser b'nidvas nafsho v'shema'asav
yoser retzuyim ומשום הכי אמרינן דנדר הוא הרי עלי שאינו מתנדב לגמרי.
u'mishum hachi amrinan d'neder hu harei alai she'eino misnadev l'gamrei.
So that's why he says maybe that's reflected in the idea that
even by a קרבן korban נדר neder is הרי עלי harei alai
because you're not yet giving it. You're promising to give it in
the future. So it shows a certain degree of hesitation. כיוון שלא
הפרישו עכשיו keivan shelo hifrisho achshav ונדבה הוא באומר הרי זו לפי
שמתנדב נדרו יותר לרצון
u'nedavah hu b'omer harei zo
lefi shemisnadev nidro yoser l'ratzon וכיוון שזהו פירושם של נדר ונדבה v'keivan
shezehu peirusham shel neder u'nedavah
and that's how by a קרבן korban it maps onto how unhesitatingly
you're doing it, so אף בנזיר af b'nazir אע"פ af al pi
שאין נדרה של נזירות אלא בעניין אחד she'ein nidrah shel nezirus ela
b'inyan echad because you say הריני נזיר, hareini nazir, מי שכוונתו שלו
רצויה יותר קרויה נזירתו נדבה. mi shekavanaso shelo retzuya yoser keruya neziroso
nedavah. If you're doing it for the right religious reasons, then your
act of נזירות nezirus was an act of a נדבה, nedavah, a
gift to God, as it were. ומי שאינו רצוי כל כך קרוי
נדר, u'mi she'eino ratzuy kol kach karuy neder, then your act of
נזירות nezirus is like something you forbade on
yourself but we don't call it like a giving to God. So
how much you identify like a gift to God or do we
say something is more like something you did to yourself. Okay. And
that's why he says that's why we say that if that's the
definition, then a נדר neder works for רשע, rasha, not a real
רשע rasha but whatever but non-unambiguous כשר, kasher, and נדבה nedavah is
for a כשר. kasher. Okay now, what's the why doesn't it have
שבועה shvua in the end of the משנה? mishna? Right, why doesn't
it say if you say כנדבת כשרים k'nidvos kesherim it also works
for a שבועה. shvua. And here the basic reason is is because
כשרים kesherim never take שבועות. shvuos. That's right.
The ר"ן Ran says it earlier.
The idea is that שבועות shvuos is always this problem of שם
שמיים לבטלה shem shamayim l'vatala and there's a general sense which we'll
see later but
whatever that you I mean it's actually there's an interesting רש"י Rashi
רמב"ן Ramban על התורה al hatorah about this, which is ובשמו תשבע,
u'vishmo tishaveia, right, the פסוק pasuk ובשמו תשבע u'vishmo tishaveia says what's
the פסוק? pasuk? את ה' אלקיך תירא ואותו תעבוד ובו תדבק ובשמו
תשבע. Es Hashem Elokecha tira v'oso sa'avod u'vo sidbak u'vishmo tishaveia. So
רש"י Rashi says מי שיש בו כל המידות הללו mi she'yesh bo
kol hamiddos halalou את ה' אלקיך תירא ואותו תעבוד ובו תדבק, Es
Hashem Elokecha tira v'oso sa'avod u'vo sidbak, then that person ובשמו תשבע,
u'vishmo tishaveia, but that there could
be a time when somebody is at the right מדריגה madreiga that
it would be appropriate to take a שבועה בשם השם. shvua b'shem
Hashem. But everybody else, not. And I believe the רמב"ן Ramban there
argues and he says it's never appropriate to take a שבועה, shvua,
like it means like בשמו bishmo as opposed to if you're going
to take a שבועה, shvua, you better do it in God's name
and not in the name of some other god. But anyway, but
that's a question. Like since the שבועה shvua is about taking God's
name, can it ever be appropriate religious act? Because you could see
to take an oath in the name of God is calling God
as your witness, maybe you can see that as a proper religious
act. On the other hand, because of the consequence of לא ינקה
ה' את אשר ישא את שמו לשוא. lo yenakeh Hashem es asher
yisa es shemo lashav.
The consequence of taking God's name in vain. And we just learned
yesterday that somebody who hears somebody say שם שמיים shem shamayim has
to put him in
חרם, cherem, right, שם שמיים לבטלה, shem shamayim l'vatala, the non-weighty use
of God's name. There could be something intrinsically complicated and problematic by
taking a שבועה. shvua. So therefore the משנה mishna says if you're
saying that I want this to work like כשרים kesherim would do
this type of an act, so could be that therefore that never
allows it therefore for to be a binding שבועה shvua because that
would not be the thing that a כשר kasher would do. Charlie?
When I served on a grand jury I we were sworn in
and they said you can affirm rather than swear and the guy
looked at me directly as if by
my יארמולקע yarmulke
implying that I was not going to swear.
Right, there you go. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says like
this. So that's a good Jewish practice is never to take a
שבועה. shvua.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this. ודילמא הכי קאמר. V'dilma
hachi ka'amar. Okay, so that's the basic point of the משנה. mishna.
But the part that's missing of the משנה mishna as opposed to
the qualifier כנדרי רשעים k'nidrei resha'im כנדבת כשרים k'nidvas kesherim etc. is
what's the end of your sentence? How do we know what you're
trying to say? So the גמרא Gemara says ודילמא הכי קאמר, v'dilma
hachi ka'amar, maybe what you're trying to say is like this: כנדרי
רשעים לא נדרנא. K'nidrei resha'im lo nadarna. I won't take an oath
like the נדרים nedarim of רשעים. resha'im. How do we know that
you mean how do we know you mean to say like the
נדרים nedarim of רשעים resha'im this should be forbidden or this should
be a קרבן korban or whatever you're saying? So the גמרא Gemara
says אמר שמואל Amar Shmuel באומר כנדרי רשעים הריני עלי והימנו. b'omer
k'nidrei resha'im hareini alai v'himenu. So these are three different statements. You
say כנדרי רשעים הריני k'nidrei resha'im hareini like the נדרים nedarim of
רשעים resha'im behold I am, and then you have to fill in
the blank with behold I am a נזיר. nazir. נזירות. nezirut. Well,
maybe there's another way of construing it. Like the נדרי רשעים, nidrei
reshaim, it is on me. What's on me? כנדרי רשעים kenidrei reshaim
from it. I won't eat from it. Okay, so that's like a
יד, yad, some of the critical part of the sentence is missing
of course. It seemed to me that that's not much of a
יד, yad, you know, which is what the גמרא Gemara is going
to ask, so let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara.
Okay, הריני בנזירות. hareini binezirut. So here's what you mean. Behold I
am in a state of being a נזיר. nazir. עלי, alai, this
is for on me. בקרבן bekorban as a קרבן. korban. I should
by the way mention there is a debate between תוספות Tosafot and
the ר"ן Ran what בקרבן bekorban means here. Whether בקרבן bekorban means
a classic קרבן, korban, like I obligate myself to bring an עולה.
olah. I obligate, or I make this into an עולה. olah. That's
a נדר neder and נדבה, nedavah, that's the classic נדר ונדבה neder
unedavah distinction. The other possibility תוספות Tosafot says, that's what the ר"ן
Ran says, because it works better with the whole נדר ונדבה. neder
unedavah. The other possibility תוספות Tosafot says is that no, בקרבן bekorban
means like קונם, konam, okay? That you're actually saying that this piece
of bread is forbidden עלי alai קונם konam like a קרבן. korban.
And it's just a classic נדרי איסור. nidrei issur. Okay, so that's
what he says בקרבן bekorban means and הימנו heimenu that I won't
eat from it בשבועה bishvuah as a שבועה. shvuah. By the way,
the תוספות's Tosafot read is better because if you remember like the
three classic sort of types of הפלאה hafla'ah that we're dealing with
that aren't שייך shayach to סדר קדשים Seder Kodashim is נדר, neder,
נזיר, nazir, and a שבועה, shvuah, right? So the נדר neder part
is the קרבן korban according to תוספות. Tosafot. Anyway, so that's how
we have to fill in the blank and I won't eat from
it, a שבועה shvuah that I won't eat from it. So the
גמרא Gemara says, the גמרא Gemara now questions, okay, you told me
at least a trigger word here, but how do you know how
to fill in the blank?
הריני נזירות. hareini nezirut. What do you mean behold I am in
a נזירות? nezirut? How do you know that's how you fill in
the blank? דילמא הריני בתענית קאמר? dilma hareini betaanit kaamar? Maybe I
should be in a תענית, taanit, you know, maybe I should be,
I don't know, a lot of things. And even if there's a
clear type of you know religious context, there's more than one meaning.
So it's at least a יד שאינה מוכיח yad she'einah mochiach and
the גמרא Gemara actually says, you know, and this is שמואל Shmuel
talking, and we know שמואל Shmuel holds a יד שאינה מוכיח yad
she'einah mochiach is no good, but you could even say further, maybe
it's not even a יד שאינה מוכיח, yad she'einah mochiach, maybe it's
not a יד yad at all, like there's so many things you
could mean. Okay, so how do we know you mean that you
want to be a נזיר? nazir? So אמר שמואל כשהיה נזיר עובר
לפניו. amar Shmuel keshehayah nazir over lefanav.
Alright, a lot of things we're reading into the משנה. Mishnah. There
was a נזיר nazir walking in front of you and you said
הריני. hareini. So clearly you meant הריני נזיר. hareini nazir. Okay, but
the כנדרי כשרים kenidrei kesherim or כנדרי רשעים, kenidrei reshaim, that's the
חידוש chiddush of the משנה. Mishnah. And while normally, right, it seems
we get frustrated, you know, when the גמרא Gemara does crazy אוקימתות
okimtot to explain a משנה. Mishnah. So first of all it missed
the key word הריני. hareini. Second of all it missed the key
fact that a נזיר nazir was walking in front of you. Okay,
fine, but you know what? I actually don't think that that's the
issue of the משנה. Mishnah. The issue of the משנה Mishnah is
when you add the qualifier כנדרי רשעים kenidrei reshaim or כנדרי כשרים,
kenidrei kesherim, כנדבות רשעים kenidvot reshaim or כנדבות כשרים. kenidvot kesherim. The
end of the sentence is however that sentence is going to end.
You have a sentence that normally would be interpreted as נזירות, nezirut,
נדר, neder, קרבן, korban, whatever. The question is what is the meaning
when you add this qualifier at the beginning. So the משנה Mishnah
is not really focused on dealing with the end of the sentence.
Okay, which is why actually the ר"ן Ran says, even if you
were explicit, even if you said כנדרי רשעים כיכר זה עלי קונם,
kenidrei reshaim kikar zeh alai konam, okay, that that's still the חידוש
chiddush of the משנה Mishnah because if you say כנדרי רשעים kenidrei
reshaim it works, but if you say כנדרי כשרים כיכר זה עלי
קונם kenidrei kesherim kikar zeh alai konam it wouldn't work. The sentence
could have been totally explicit. The חידוש chiddush of the משנה Mishnah
is the first qualifier, what that you know whether that sort of
says that it should or shouldn't work, whether that's a, whether that's
a phenomenon נדרי רשעים, nidrei reshaim, נדרי כשרים. nidrei kesherim. The תוספות
Tosafot disagrees. תוספות Tosafot says it's only because the end of the
sentence is somewhat ambiguous, so therefore if you actually said כנדרי כשרים
כיכר זה עלי קונם kenidrei kesherim kikar zeh alai konam it would
be אסור. assur. But if, given that there's an element of a
יד yad going on here and it's not exactly clear how to
end the sentence and there's some ambiguity, therefore when that qualifier is
something that like normally doesn't work, or like isn't a sort of
thing, you know, נדרי כשרים, nidrei kesherim, you know, then we don't
interpret your sentence, then we mean that, whether you know your commitment
to make this thing אסור assur is more ambiguous and therefore we'll
say it won't be effective. But if your sentence was completely unambiguous,
this qualifier in the beginning wouldn't matter. Okay, so that's an interesting
debate of the ר"ן Ran and תוספות Tosafot whether we have to
be talking about an ambiguous end. But the way the ר"ן Ran
reads it, and in a way I think it's just simpler to
read it in the גמרא, Gemara, is that the emphasis here is
not on the rest of the sentence. We can say the rest
of the sentence is whatever you said. There was a נזיר nazir
walking in front of you. You explicitly said הריני נזיר. hareini nazir.
Said whatever you wanted to say. The חידוש chiddush of the משנה
Mishnah is that the beginning clause, how much
does that determine whether or not the rest of the sentence will
or won't take effect? Yes.
How magically potent is the sense of language here in terms of
הריני? hareini? In other words, from my own subjective reality. Like הריני
כהן. hareini kohen. A כהן kohen walks by.
הריני אישה. hareini ishah.
הריני... hareini... Well, obviously only... things that you can effect yourself. Although
the ר"ן Ran does ask whether there is a question between אהיה
Ehieh and הריני. Hareini. You know, the ר"ן Ran says that isn't
there a, you know, another גמרא Gemara that says if you say
אהיה נזיר, Ehieh Nazir, it works and, you know, is the fact
of הריני Hareini any different than the word אהיה? Ehieh? So he
has a little bit of a discussion like that. But obviously it
only works in things where you can actually create those statuses. Yes.
Who's gonna use this phrase? Who's gonna say 'like the wicked' when
they want to...
To say it themselves. Yeah, that's an excellent point too. Like, why
would somebody even say כנדרי רשעים Kenidrei Reshaim if they're trying to
make it take effect? I don't know. It's a real curious question.
Like that's why I said this משנה Mishnah is such a strange,
you know... It's such a dense משנה. Mishnah. Unless it's a way
also that the משנה Mishnah is using it as a way of
communicating a certain displeasure with the whole phenomenon of נדרים Nedarim and
נזירות Nezirot and so on. You know, now you remember that the...
we talked about the whole idea of קונם Konam and one of...
of כינויים Kinnuyim and one of the points of כינויים Kinnuyim was
essentially because of to get people to avoid these types of languages,
right? And that maybe the whole taking of נדרים Nedarim was too
prevalent, right? And they wanted, thank you, to create either more technical
language or language that... no no, sorry, thank you... a language that
actually would like, you know, prevent people or so to, you know,
from maybe overly doing it. So I think the משנה Mishnah could
be trying to communicate a certain displeasure with the phenomenon, you know,
as a way telling a הלכה Halacha that communicates that displeasure. But
you're right, like who's gonna take a vow and say, 'Oh, this
is אסור Asur to me like the way רשעים Reshaim would take
נדרים.' Nedarim. It's bizarre. All right, but anyway bottom line is that
we're saying the end of the sentence was clear enough and the
חידוש Chidush is the beginning. And again the ר"ן Ran says even
if the end of sentence was 100% explicit, the beginning would trigger
whether or not it would take effect. Okay, now we're gonna look
at the rest of the sentence.
Yes, that's what תוספות's Tosafot's point too, right? When he says it's
the very
very first תוספות Tosafot of רבי אליעזר משפירא, Rabbi Eliezer MiSpira, he's
גורס Gores קונם בהדיא, Konam Behedya, אם כנדרי כשרים, Im Kenidrei Kesherim,
אפילו הכי, Afilu Hachi, right?
Right, but then תוספות Tosafot goes on to have a question about
that. But in the beginning he says that he's correct, תוספות Tosafot
says that explicitly at the beginning and then he, like the ר"ן,
Ran, and then he goes on later and he questions that. Yes.
If we're saying the end is not ambiguous, it's clearly defined, this
כנדרי כשרים Kenidrei Kesherim has evolved into our
בלי נדר?
Bli Neder? Something like that, that's true.
That's a cute point. That's a cute point that I hadn't thought
about. But you're right, that כנדרי כשרים Kenidrei Kesherim means like with
a certain, right, I don't really want to do it so I'm
not promising. Yeah. David Scharf told me once that he's developing, he's
gonna write this Jewish lexicon, so like as like translation of Jewish
phrases. So it was like, what was it? It was like, אם
ירצה השם Im Yirtze Hashem means if someone else is paying for
it.
בלי נדר Bli Neder means maybe. בלי נדר Bli Neder means maybe.
ברוך השם Baruch Hashem means none of your darn business.
All right.
All right, so I cleaned that one up a little bit. Okay,
so now back to the bit. All right, so it says like
this: So, הימנו, Hemenu, so if you say right, כנדרי רשעים הימנו
Kenidrei Reshaim Hemenu from it, בשבועה Bishvua that means an oath that
I won't eat from it. דילמא הימנו דאכילה קאמר, Dilma Hemenu Deachila
Kamar, maybe it means I will I will eat from it. How
do you even know it means a שבועה Shvua anything? אמר רבא:
Amar Rava: דאמר הימנו שלא אוכל. Deamar Hemenu Shelo Ochal. Now here
it sounds like you really are explicit. Okay, no, you say 'from
it I won't eat'. אי הכי מאי איריא? I Hachi Mai Irya?
So what's the חידוש? Chidush? מהו דתימא הלא מפיק שבועה מפומיה, Mahu
Deteima Halo Mafik Shvua Mipumei,
you didn't say שבועה Shvua I won't eat, you just said I
won't eat. קא משמע לן, Kamah Shmalan, so some take out the
word הריני. Hareini. קא משמע לן Kamah Shmalan that even when you
don't say the word שבועה, Shvua, if you say I won't eat
from it, then the idea of שבועה Shvua is a יד. Yad.
So this point seems to be saying no, part of the חידוש
Chidush is that you're not explicit. Ignoring the opening qualifier כנדרי כשרים
Kenidrei Kesherim or כנדרי רשעים, Kenidrei Reshaim, the part of the point
here is you didn't say the whole sentence and nevertheless it's binding
because of a יד. Yad. So because they're kosher, right? I know,
but the point is that the גמרא Gemara here even if you
just said 'I won't eat from it', that the חידוש Chidush is
that that's a יד לשבועה Yad Lishvua and it means a שבועה
Shvua you won't eat from it. So it's clear that the גמרא
Gemara thinks that part of the חידוש Chidush of this משנה Mishnah
is not the opening qualifier, but that the rest of the sentence
is also a יד Yad and we fill in the blank, okay?
And you don't have part of... and you don't have to say
the keyword שבועה. Shvua. But in addition, the major focus of this
משנה Mishnah is on the opening qualifier. Yes, Charlie.
Yeah, so it could have made a distinction between something that could
have been made a קרבן Korban versus something that couldn't. Like a
loaf of bread could never be a קרבן. Korban.
Right, that gets to תוספות's Tosafot's question about whether by the word
קרבן Korban we mean קרבן Korban or we mean קונם. Konam.
Yeah, yeah.
But if you didn't... excuse me, preface it with כנדרי רשעים Kenidrei
Reshaim or כשרים, Kesherim, whatever it is, and you said the rest
of that, no one would say that if I just say, okay,
I'm gonna eat this, you know, I'm gonna eat breakfast today, that
I'm taking a שבועה Shvua to eat breakfast, right?
Well, look, that gets back to the גמרא's Gemara's question
about אשנה פרק זה נדר גדול לאלוהי ישראל. Ashana Perek Zeh Neder
Gadol Leilohei Yisrael. When
do you...
And this is not religious at all, like eating breakfast, right?
I mean, people take שבועות shevuot for a lot of things. Again,
you're right, you need context. You're absolutely correct. You know, those words
themselves could just be normal speech, right?
Like אשכים ואשנה פרק זה ashkim v'eshneh perek zeh could be normal
speech. How do you know when there- when is the weighty enough
context to show that that's what you're committing to? It's a very
good point. You're right, I think that there is, you know, context
is critical there. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay, so it says, כנדרי רשעים לומר קים כנדבותם נדר בנזיר. k'nidrei
reshaim lomar qum k'nidvotam neder b'nazir. Now we're going to use this
to get into this discussion about the difference between נדר neder and
נדבה. nedava. So מן תנא דשני ליה בין נדר לנדבה? man tanna
dishni lei bein neder l'nedava? Who has a difference between נדר neder
and נדבה? nedava? לימא לא רבי מאיר ולא רבי יהודה? leima lo
Rabbi Meir v'lo Rabbi Yehuda? Not רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and not
רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. This now becomes a perfect opportunity to discuss
the values of making a נדר. neder. דתניא, d'tanya, we taught in
a ברייתא: Baraisa: טוב אשר לא תדור משתדור ולא תשלם. tov asher
lo tiddor mishetiddor v'lo tishalem. The end of the פסוק pasuk is
את אשר תדור שלם. et asher tiddor shalem. Is that the לשון?
lashon? What you the vow that you take, fulfill it. טוב אשר
לא תדור משתדור ולא תשלם, tov asher lo tiddor mishetiddor v'lo tishalem,
right? Better though not to take a vow than to take it
and not fulfill it. Alright, so that kind of obvious what it
means, don't think that the very act of taking a vow is
a religious act and that if you don't want and then don't
worry about whether in the- a lot of people feel that way,
right? You know, the spirit hits them and they make a big,
and they raise their hand in the שול shul appeal or whatever,
you know, and they think that there's something intrinsically valuable about doing
that. No, be aware that if you're not going to fulfill it,
it's better you should have never done it in the first place.
Okay, but the question is, what about doing it and fulfilling it?
So what's the story there? So טוב מזה ומזה שאינו נודר כל
עיקר דברי רבי מאיר. tov mizeh umizeh she'eino noder kol ikar divrei
Rabbi Meir. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says the best is not even
doing it and fulfilling it, the best is don't make נדרים. nedarim.
Do focus on your religious obligations, don't try to do anything extra,
you know, for and that could be for one of two reasons.
Why is it better not to do it and fulfill it? One
could be because there's always the risk you won't, so it's better
as a principle not to start doing these types of things because
it's too risky, okay, and it's just not good practice because of
this possibility that you won't. The other answer is that maybe in
general, you know, religion should be approached as a sense of heteronomous
responsibility, sort of divinely imposed obligations, right?
Not what is this word you're saying?
Heteronomous, right? Not heteronomous,
it's the difference of autonomous. What is it? Isn't it heteronomy? Right,
autonomy is sort of rule by oneself and heteronomy is rule imposed
by others. Okay, anyway, pretty sure. Okay, anyway,
so
that your עבודת השם avodat Hashem should be what God demands of
you. You know, you have your own religious impulses and desires or
whatever, that's just serving your own religious impulses, that's not true עבודת
השם. avodat Hashem. Okay, it could be a fundamental idea of that,
you know. Now of course it's funny like there are other times
where like כל נדיב לבו יביאנה, kol nediv libo yevi'enah, you know,
את אשר ידבנו לבו. et asher yidvenu libo. So okay, if
the שול shul needs a donation, you should make a donation, but
you want to start making נדרים nedarim just in a vacuum? You
know, maybe that's intrinsically not a good phenomenon. That's a different way
of thinking about it. It's important what the גמרא Gemara doesn't quote
here but it quotes elsewhere
is
כל הנודר כאילו בנה במה וכל המקיימו כאילו
הקריב עליה קרבן.
kol hanoder k'ilu banah bamah v'chol hamkaymo k'ilu hikriv aleha
korban. Right now, okay, so it's great, you made a במה bamah
and you brought a קרבן korban on it, wonderful, you did a
religious act, except really, are במות bamot always a good phenomenon? You
know, if there's a central בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and there's a
good, healthy religious sort of establishment in place, you know, going off
on your own is not necessarily a good thing, right? On the
other hand, there are times where we don't have a good healthy
religious establishment in place and it's a time of היתר במות heter
bamot and that's how people fundamentally serve God. So it raises I
think those interesting questions about the nature of sort of personal religious
experience as opposed to sort of communal
and sort of imposed from above. And that's one way of- so
it's interesting to ask what is this idea, you know, that it's
better not to make a נדר neder even if you're going to
fulfill it. Is it because of the possibility of non-fulfillment or there's
something intrinsically religiously problematic with it? Yes.
Heteronomy definition in English: subjection to something else, especially a lack of
moral freedom or self-determination, first
used 1798.
There you go. Okay, so that's what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says.
רבי יהודה אומר טוב מזה ומזה נודר ומשלם. Rabbi Yehuda omer tov
mizeh umizeh noder umshalem. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says no, best is
if you're able to make the נדר neder and fulfill it, that
would be the best. So anyway, getting back to us, what's our
משנה Mishna that says נדרי רשעים? nidrei reshaim? So it doesn't seem
like רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, right? רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda seems to
feel
that נדרים nedarim is a good thing. Why doesn't it not seem
like רבי מאיר? Rabbi Meir? Because
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says נדרים nedarim is not a good thing.
But the משנה Mishna seems to say that נדבות nedavot are a
good thing and we don't know that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir would
distinguish between the two. So the גמרא Gemara goes to... The easiest
response is, אפילו תימא רבי מאיר, Afilu Teima Rabbi Meir, it is
רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. כי קאמר רבי מאיר בנדר, בנדבה לא קאמר.
Ki Kama Rabbi Meir BeNeder, BeNedava Lo Kama. It's the נדר Neder
that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir has a problem with, okay. א נדבה
A Nedava he does not. Now again, by the way, getting back
to my heteronomy autonomy issue, we could actually understand a difference between
נדר Neder and נדבה Nedava different than we said before. Right before
we were trying to understand what's the big difference. A נדר Neder
you might not fulfill it and a נדבה Nedava you might not
fulfill it or a נדבה Nedava you might wind up being misusing
the קרבן Korban if you make something an עולה. Olah. But there
is a difference in that a נדר Neder creates a religious obligation
that you have imposed upon yourself, right, as opposed to a נדבה
Nedava you're just sanctifying something. So you could actually say that to
create a sense of religious obligation coming from somewhere other than God,
right, is intrinsically, you know, problematic. Whereas a נדבה Nedava where you're
not creating an obligation, you're just sanctifying an object, right, there's not
creating that other sense of you in a sense obligating yourself, which
is sort of the נדר Neder phenomenon. So that's an interesting possibility
of why the distinction. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara doesn't elaborate on it—well,
it will elaborate on it in a minute—but it says yes, according
to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, רשעים Reshaim make נדרים, Nedarim, טוב מזה
ומזה שאינו נודר כל עיקר, Tov MiZe UMiZe SheEino Noder Kol Ikar,
but נדבות Nedavot would be okay. So the גמרא Gemara says, בנדבה
לא קאמר. BeNedava Lo Kama. והא קתני כנדבתם, VeHa Katani KiNedvatam, if
you say like the נדבות Nedavot of רשעים, Reshaim, נדר ונזיר וקרבן,
Neder VeNazir VeKorban, so why do we say כנדבתם נדר, KiNedvatam Nadar,
right? Because it should be because if it's like their נדבה, Nedava,
it should say like if they're making a נדר Neder then it's
not a נדבה Nedava if a נדר Neder is a bad thing
and a נדבה Nedava is a good thing. תני נדב בנזיר ובקרבן.
Tani Nadav BeNazir UVeKorban. Okay, and a lot of ראשונים Rishonim say
the גמרא Gemara could have just asked that on the משנה Mishnah
itself. Why does it say
כנדבתם נדר, KiNedvatam Nadar, should have said כנדבתם נדב. KiNedvatam Nadav. Anyway,
what we're saying is that for רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, נדר Neder
is a bad phenomenon, that's נדרי רשעים, Nidrei Reshaim, that's why it's
a meaningful statement. נדבה Nedava is a good phenomenon, so therefore only
it's
a נדבה Nedava of a רשע Rasha is not meaningful, a נדבה
Nedava of a כשר Kasher is meaningful. So now the גמרא's Gemara
going to ask what's the difference. מאי שנא נודר דלא? Mai Shna
Noder DeLo? Why is a נדר Neder not a good phenomenon for
רבי מאיר? Rabbi Meir? דלמא אתי לידי תקלה. Dilma Ati Lidei Takala.
So now the גמרא Gemara rather than the sort of nice theological
philosophical point I was making seems to say no, the only real
problem with a נדר Neder even according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
is that you won't fulfill it. And therefore you shouldn't make it
at all. So if that's true, why is a נדבה Nedava any
better?
נדבה נמי לא,
דלמא אתי לידי תקלה.
Nedava Nami
Lo, Dilma Ati Lidei Takala.
So the גמרא Gemara says no, כהלל הזקן. KeHillel HaZaken. No, there's
a way to do a נדבה Nedava which is unproblematic like הלל.
Hillel. דתניא, אמרו עליו על הלל הזקן שלא מעל אדם בעולתו כל
ימיו. DeTanya, Amru Alav Al Hillel HaZaken SheLo Maal Adam BeOlato Kol
Yamav. Nobody ever did מעילה Meila with his קרבן. Korban. מביא כשהיא
חולין לעזרה, Mevia KeSheHi Chulin LaAzara,
he brought it unsanctified into the courtyard, up to the courtyard, probably
not into the courtyard itself.
כשהיא חולין לעזרה, KeSheHi Chulin LaAzara, right?
חוץ לעזרה, Chutz LaAzara, right? ומקדישה, UMakdisha, and he would sanctify it,
וסומך עליה, VeSomech Aleha, and then he would do שחיטה Shechita a
second later, ושוחטה, VeShochta, and slaughtered. Now I said like why can't
you also do the same with a נדר? Neder? You know, you
wait till it's a second before you bring it, you make a
נדר Neder and then you sanctify it and so forth. You can,
but that just adds another step, right? Because in the end it's
going you're going to have to sanctify the animal anyway, so as
you're standing there right at the door of the בית המקדש, Beit
HaMikdash, why would you first take a נדר, Neder, then sanctify it,
then bring it? Just straight sanctify it. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says by a נדר Neder you, a נדבה Nedava you can completely
avoid, you never have that sense of a personal obligation you might
not fulfill. All you have is the end result of giving a
קרבן. Korban. And you give the קרבן Korban in the way where
there's never any time that something wrong might come of it, okay.
As soon as you focus on creating a personal obligation, you know,
it's always like dangerous business, maybe you will maybe you won't. If
you here the focus is not that, the focus is on you
just give a קרבן Korban and you give it in a way
where there's no possibility that there will be any misuse. So a
נדבה Nedava of כשרים Kesherim is possible that it won't lead, it's
possible to have a נדבה Nedava of כשרים. Kesherim. Now one minute,
תוספות Tosafot and the ר"ן Ran ask, does that mean that if
you say כנדבת כשרים הרי זו עולה, KeNedvat Kesherim Harei Zu Olah,
you have to be standing at the door of the בית המקדש
Beit HaMikdash or else it doesn't work? Doesn't sound that way from
the משנה. Mishnah. So תוספות Tosafot says no. תוספות Tosafot says since
there is such a phenomenon as נדבת כשרים, Nedvat Kesherim, there's a
way to do a נדבה Nedava in a total 100 percent כשר,
Kasher, unproblematic way, the phrase כנדבת כשרים KeNedvat Kesherim works. I could
say this should be effective as the נדבה Nedava of כשרים Kesherim
people. And there is such a thing as a נדבה Nedava of
כשרים Kesherim people in a very particular set of circumstances. So therefore
this is effective like the נדבה Nedava of כשרים Kesherim people. But
there's no such thing as a נדר Neder of כשרים Kesherim people,
okay, and therefore I say it's effective like the נדר, Neder, if
a person was really כשר Kasher they wouldn't be making the נדר
Neder so it would not be effective. Okay, so it doesn't have
to mean that in the משנה Mishnah you're standing at the door
of the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. It just means that the concept
of a נדבה Nedava of a כשרים Kesherim people, that concept does
exist. All right. people, but there's no such thing as a נדר
neder of כשר kosher people, but there's no such thing
as a נדר neder of כשר kasher people. Okay? And therefore I
say it's effective like the נדר. neder. If a person was really
כשר, kasher, they wouldn't be making the נדר, neder, so it would
not be effective. Okay, so it doesn't have to mean that in
the משנה Mishnah you're standing at the door of the בית המקדש.
Beis Hamikdash. It just means that the concept of a נדבה nedavah
of a כשר kasher people, that concept does exist. All right. There
was a question? No? Okay. Yes. Just this minor point that it
looks like the person who brought the קרבן korban is
שחט-ing shecht it.
Well, you could. In theory, you could. זר כשר בשחיטה,
zar
kasher b'shchita, but that's true.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says, תניח נדבה דקרבנות, tanich nedavah
d'korbanos, fine, so we have an idea that a כשר kasher person,
the idea of a נדבה nedavah of כשרים ksherim is a phenomenon
that exists by קרבנות. korbanos. נדבה דנזירות מאי איכא למימר? nedavah d'nezirus
mai ika l'meimar? Where is there an idea that a נזיר Nazir
can be a נדבה, nedavah, again reading this the ר"ן's Ran way,
which is not a technical legal difference of how you say הרי
עלי harei alai or הרי זו, harei zu, but it means a
purely
religious act of נזירות? nezirus? So, is that really true? So, the
question why the גמרא Gemara thinks that it might not be, you
know, maybe it's informed by the idea that the גמרא Gemara says
about אשר חטא על הנפש asher chata al hanefesh and that a
נזיר Nazir brings a קרבן חטאת, korban chatas, which, you know, so
like the whole idea of נזירות nezirus is complicated, right? So, anyway,
is that really true that that could be a pure נדבה? nedavah?
So, the גמרא Gemara says, yes, סבר לה כשמעון הצדיק, savar lah
k'Shimon Hatzadik, he holds like שמעון הצדיק, Shimon Hatzadik, דתניא, detanya, as
we taught in the ברייתא. Braisa. אמר שמעון הצדיק, amar Shimon Hatzadik,
מימי לא אכלתי אשם נזיר טמא. miyamai lo achalti asham Nazir tamei.
I never ate from the אשם asham of a נזיר טמא. Nazir
tamei. Now, because presumably, well, we'll see in a minute, but obviously
because that was problematic whether that was an appropriate that the person
who was in this situation to begin with and so on. We'll
expand on that in a minute.
אלא אחד, ela echad, one, one minute.
Let's just read. פעם אחת, paam achas, once, בא אדם אחד נזיר
מן הדרום. ba adam echad Nazir min hadarom. I saw a נזיר
Nazir come to the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, came from the south.
וראיתיו שהוא יפה עיניים, v'ra'isiv shehu yafeh einayim,
he had beautiful eyes, וטוב רואי, v'tov roi, and very handsome, וקווצותיו
סדורות לו תלתלים, v'kvutzosav sduros lo taltalim,
it's almost like from שיר השירים, Shir Hashirim, right? And his locks...
דוד המלך Dovid Hamelech too.
That's true.
דוד המלך, Dovid Hamelech, right? His locks were like layered and flowing
of his hair. אמרתי לו, אי בני, מה ראית להשחית שערך זה
הנאה? amarti lo, ai bni, mah ra'isa l'hashchis se'archa zeh hana'eh? What
made you accept the vow of נזירות nezirus which will force you
to shave your beautiful hair, cut it off? אמר לי, amar li,
he said to me, רועה הייתי לאבא בעירי. ro'eh hayisi l'aba b'iri.
I was a shepherd to my father in my city, in my
village. הלכתי למלאות מים מן המעיין. halachti l'malo'os mayim min hama'ayan. I
went to draw water from the well. ונסתכלתי בבבואה שלי. v'nistakalti b'vavuah
sheli.
I saw my reflection, ופחז עלי יצרי, v'pachaz alai yitzri, my יצר
הרע, yeitzer hara,
my lustful desires, all of a sudden seized me, וביקש לטורדני מן
העולם. v'bikeish l'tordani min ha'olam. It wanted to destroy, to take me
away from this world.
Narcissus? Right, exactly.
That's a good point. It's the reverse of the whole Narcissus story.
That's an... I hadn't thought about that, but you're right. Okay. So,
anyway, you
know, basically was trying to lead me to a life of physical
indulgence. אמרתי לו, amarti lo, I said to my יצר הרע, yeitzer
hara, רשע, rasha, למה אתה מתגאה בעולם שאינו שלך? lamah atah mitga'eh
b'olam she'eino shelcha?
Why are you, you know, glorifying yourself in a world that is
not yours? Meaning this world is temporary, you know, and fleeting. And
it's not, you know, and this isn't really, you know, it's a...
it's not...
it's not the world that we should be indulging in. במי שעתיד
להיות רימה ותולעה. b'mi she'asid lihayos rimah v'tole'ah.
You want me to sort of care about the, you know, about
the person, me, who is eventually going to be, you know, food
for the maggots. העבודה, ha'avodah, by, you know, this is like an
oath, like in... by you know, in the name of the Temple
or Heaven. שאגלחך לשמים. she'agalechacha l'shamayim. I will shave... maybe he was
talking... maybe he was talking to his hair, not to his יצר
הרע. yeitzer hara. Anyway, I will shave you for God's sake. Okay.
מיד עמדתי ונישקתיו על ראשו. miyad amadti v'nishaktiv al rosho.
I stood up and kissed him on his head. אמרתי לו, amarti
lo, I said, בני, כמוך ירבו נוזרי נזירות בישראל. bni, kamochah yirbu
nozrei nezirus b'Yisrael. Oh, for you... like you there should be like
the people who take נזירות nezirus in ישראל, Yisrael, that
they do it truly לשם שמים.
l'shem shamayim. עליך הכתוב אומר, aleicha hakasuv omer,
regarding you the verse says, איש כי יפלי לנדור נדר נזיר להזיר
להשם. ish ki yaifli lindor neder Nazir l'hazir l'Hashem. It's להשם. l'Hashem.
And you can understand that, right? Because, you know, it's always that
thing, like, you know, if you go ahead and you adopt this
whole role of asceticism or whatever. I mean, you know, it's clear
from the נביאים Nevi'im that the נזירים Nezirim were like an identifiable
group of people that were striving for a higher like religious status,
right? It says like ואשקה את הנזירים יין ולנביאים אמרתי לא תנבאו.
va'ashkeh es haNezirim yayin v'laNevi'im amarti lo tinavu. So, you know, so
like
it's always a question. Somebody is adopting all of these types of
פרום-קייט. frumkeit. How much are they doing it לשם שמים l'shem shamayim
and how much are they doing it so that it makes them
feel good about how פרום frum they're being, or it makes other
people look at them in a particular way and puts them in
a different class in society, right? So there's always those questions about
when people are especially in ways that are sort of visibly separating
themselves, right? It's not just a private פרום-קייט, frumkeit, it's something that
visibly is signaling how you're different and separate from the rest of
society. So you could understand why there's a real concern about how
pure is the motivation. But here's somebody that is doing... what?
How do we translate ביקש לטורדני? bikeish l'tordani?
To waste me away from... from the world. And actually it's funny
because the world
means...
Exactly.
Okay, so here it was actually, you know, for very pure reasons,
completely unselfish or un, you know, purely religious reasons. So that’s, so
anyway, it’s possible that there would be an uncomplicated נזיר, nazir, or
a נדבה nedava of a נזיר. nazir. So now the גמרא Gemara
asks about this. So the גמרא Gemara says, מתקיף לה רב מני
מאי שנא אשם טמא דלא אכל? Matkif leh Rav Mani mai shna
asham temei de-lo achal? מתקיף Matkif because this is really more of
a point of clarification rather than a challenge. But anyway, מאי שנא
אשם נזיר טמא דלא אכל? mai shna asham nazir temei de-lo achal?
Why would שמעון הצדיק Shimon HaTzadik not eat the אשם asham of
a נזיר טמא? nazir temei? דאתי אחטא, de-ati acheit,
because it’s coming for a sin that he became טמא. temei. כל
אשם נמי לא ליכול, kol asham nami lo leachul, he shouldn’t eat
any אשם, asham, דאחטא אתי, de-acheit ati, because it’s coming to atone
for a sin. אמר ליה רב יונה, Amar leh Rav Yonah, so
רב יונה Rav Yonah responded back, היינו טעמא, hainu ta'ama, this is
the reason. כשהן תוהין, kishe'hen tohin, because when they become טמא temei
and they have to restart their נזירות nezirot all over again, they
like, you know, become, like,
astounded or regretful. And, I’m sorry, so, I jumped ahead. כשהן תוהין,
kishe'hen tohin, when they are, like, you know, worked up over their
own religious state and they feel that they’re sinners and they want
to make themselves better, נוזרין, nozrin, then they decide to become a
נזיר. nazir. וכשהן מיטמאין, ukshe'hen mitamein,
then when they become טמא, temei, ורבים עליהם ימי נזירות, verabbim aleihem
yemei nezirot, and then it extends longer than they had expected, מתחרטין
בהן, mitchartin bahen,
then they say, "Oh, I never should have become this," because they’re
not really doing it because they’re really, you know, it was like
an impetuous type of a thing. Like, you feel bad and shameful
about where you are religiously, so you want to do something about
it, so you decide you’re going to be a נזיר. nazir. Okay,
so on the one hand, you could say this is coming from
a religious perspective—you’re trying to put yourself on a better path—but it’s
coming from a certain impetuosity and from a certain sense of, like,
more of like guilt than out of a sense of a deep
conviction. So therefore, because it’s not coming from a deep conviction, if
it gets hard, then you wish you never would have done it
in the end. You don’t have the, you know, you don’t have
the endurance for it. ונמצאו מביאין חולין לעזרה, venimtze'u mevi'in chullin la'azarah,
and it’s as if, not literally, but it’s as if they’re bringing
חולין לעזרה. chullin la'azarah. So the point is that שמעון הצדיק, Shimon
HaTzadik, it’s interesting, it’s like, you know, a normal נזיר nazir who
never became טמא, temei, you know, you could say maybe that person
is always good. Maybe he only had a problem with those that
became טמא. temei. You know, you could have said something that the
גמרא Gemara also didn’t say, which is that if you became טמא,
temei, maybe it shows that you weren’t as careful as you needed
to have been. You know, you could have sort of made it
about other things. But the גמרא, Gemara, interestingly, you know, a, well,
first of all, you know, the תורה Torah when it describes a
נזיר nazir says, כי ימות עליו מת בפתח פתאום, ki yamut alav
met befetah pitom, that people sometimes become טמא temei and it has
nothing to do with their fault. So we don’t want to assume
any fault about that. But still, wants to say, like, you know,
if once it becomes טמא, temei, then he would like seriously question
whether this person, now that it’s schlepping on, is still really, seriously,
you know, remains as deeply committed to being a נזיר, nazir, you
know, as maybe they started out. And this was the one guy
that he had no questions that this was like a deep religious
conviction. Of course, what that also allows for is the fact that
somebody who didn’t become טמא, temei, maybe they more would be prepared
to say that there were people there that were of pure conviction,
you know, or at least that they didn’t have maybe, or maybe
not, maybe they had complicated convictions but they didn’t have a chance
to regret it yet; it was over quickly enough. Alright, anyway, so
it says like this: אי הכי אפילו נזיר טהור נמי. i hachi
afilu nazir tahor nami.
So if that’s true, then a נזיר טהור nazir tahor also we
should say that as soon as the immediate urge to do something
about it has passed, they regret it. לא, דאמודי אמי נפשיה דיכול
למידור. lo, de-amudei amei nafshia de-achul lemidor.
No, because that’s only 30 days. So therefore, by a נזיר טהור,
nazir tahor, even though the conviction might not have been as deep,
we don’t necessarily think that—he
could have done it for a year, though.
Okay, he, right, but we don’t think that it’s gotten to—but the
standard is 30 days. We don’t think it’s gotten to the stage
where he’s begun to regret it. Okay, so this guy, we say,
we feel that it was a very—all of the נזירים nezirim we
feel are either, you know, or feel are like not a deep
religious conviction. Some of them there hasn’t been enough time for that
to demonstrate itself, but we still think it wasn’t a deep conviction.
And some of them we actually feel that if it schleps on,
they really have lost their commitment to it. Okay, whereas this guy
we had no question. Anyway, the point being that it’s, I think
interesting especially if you think about contemporary realities, right, about people who
want to adopt—I mean the whole idea of נדר, neder, people who
are looking for חומרות, humros, people who are looking for ways to
add upon themselves religious demands, and particularly in the נזיר nazir case
in a way that very much marks them as different from the
larger society. And those types of motivations are not always pure and
uncomplicated, and are not, you know, and maybe we believe they’re לשם
שמים, leshem shamayim, but deep down they’re not, you know. And that’s
what the גמרא Gemara is sort of focusing on: the value of
making a נדר, neder, the value of being a נזיר. nazir. So
now we’re saying according to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, we’re normally skeptical
about נדרים, nedarim, and we would also normally be skeptical about נזירות,
nezirot, but there would be some circumstances where it might be actually
a type of a נדבה, nedava, a pure, a pure religious motivation.
Yes.
It's very rare that the גמרא Gemara cites someone as early as
רבי שמעון הצדיק. Rabbi Shimon HaTzadik.
That is true, but also we're looking about when there was a
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and people were becoming נזירים nazirs because they
could end it by bringing a קרבן. korban. Okay, so now let's
איבעית אימא, Iba'is eima, let's read a little bit more. If you
want, I could say,
אפילו תימא רבי יהודה. Afilu teima Rabbi Yehuda. So that was an
idea of saying רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, who normally says נדרים nedarim
are no good, would allow for the positive phenomenon of a נדבה.
nedava. Now we're going to wind up saying essentially the same about
רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, that maybe רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir would say
both נדר neder and נדבה nedava is no good, and what we
said until now for רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir we're going to say
for רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. כי אמר רבי יהודה, Ki amar Rabbi
Yehuda, when does רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda say it's טוב אשר תדור
ותשלם? tov asher tidor utshaleim? He doesn't really mean making a נדר
neder is good. He really means בנדבה. bindava. אבל בנדר לא קאמר.
Aval bineder lo ka'amar. Okay? He didn't, when he really says it's
good to do it and fulfill it, he really didn't mean through
making a נדר. neder. נדר Neder was always no good. He really
meant it's good to make a נדבה. nedava. So the גמרא Gemara
says דקתני טוב מזה ומזה נודר ומקיים. Dakatni tov mizeh umizeh noder
umekayeim. What do you mean? It says where רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
says it's best to make a נדר neder and fulfill it. He
seems like he's okay with making a נדר. neder. The גמרא Gemara
says no, תני נודב ומקיים. Tani nodev umekayeim. Alright, which is certainly
not פשט pshat at all of רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. Okay. So
מאי שנא נודר דלא? Mai shna noder d'lo? So now we're just
going to repeat what we said before except with a slightly different
variation. So basically everything we said until now for רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir we're going to say for רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. For רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says it's a good phenomenon, he meant the נדבה
nedava is a good phenomenon, a נדר neder is not a good
phenomenon. So now the גמרא Gemara says, oh, so what's the difference?
מאי שנא נודר דלא? Mai shna noder d'lo? דילמא אתי לידי
תקלה, Dilma ati lidei takala, because it'll lead to stumbling. So נדבה
נמי דילמא אתי לידי תקלה. Nedava nami dilma ati lidei takala. So
before, the benefit of this approach is before we had to quote
other people, שמעון הצדיק, Shimon HaTzadik, הלל הזקן. Hillel HaZaken.
Here we have actual statements of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that actually
speak exactly to this point. So רבי יהודה לטעמיה, Rabbi Yehuda l'taameih,
he goes according to his reasoning, he says אדם מביא כבשתו לעזרה,
Adam meivi kivshato l'azara, a person can bring his little lamb to
the עזרה, azara, ומקדישה, umakdisha, and sanctifies it there, וסומך עליה ושוחטה.
v'someich aleha v'shochta.
So exactly what we said before is what הלל הזקן Hillel HaZaken
used to do. Here we have רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda saying it.
Okay. So we're saying the same thing we said before, except here
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says some of these statements personally. Alright.
So נדר neder is bad, a נדבה nedava is good, re-reading רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda in that debate. And therefore what is an example
of a נדבה nedava that would be good, that would be unproblematic?
Making a נדבה nedava right at the doors of the בית המקדש.
Beis HaMikdash. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara goes like this: Okay,
תינח נדבה דקרבנות, Teinach nedava d'korbanos, that's a קרבן. korban. נדבה דנזירות
מאי איכא למימר? Nedava d'nezirus mai ika l'meimar? How about a נזיר?
nazir?
Where do you have that as a positive uncomplicated religious phenomenon? רבי
יהודה לטעמיה, Rabbi Yehuda l'taameih, he goes according to his reasoning, דתניא,
d'tanya, רבי יהודה אומר חסידים הראשונים היו מתאווים להביא קרבן חטאת. Rabbi
Yehuda omer chasidim harishonim hayu mis'avim l'havi korban chatas. The great, the
righteous ones wanted to bring all types of קרבנות korbanos to the
בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, but they had a little bit of a
problem, which was that how do you bring a חטאת chatas without
sinning? And they didn't want to sin. So לפי שאין הקדוש ברוך
הוא מביא תקלה על ידיהם, Lefi she'ein HaKadosh Baruch Hu meivi takala
al yadeihem,
but since God would never cause them to sin unintentionally, because you
certainly can't even intentionally sin, because then you wouldn't bring a חטאת
chatas either. The only way you bring a חטאת chatas is unintentional.
So we can't exactly, and God won't let that happen. מה היו
עושים? Mah hayu osim? What would they do? עומדים ומתנדבים נזירות למקום.
Omdim umisnadbim nezirus l'Makom.
They would make themselves a נזיר, nazir, not because they wanted to
become a נזיר. nazir. נזיר Nazir remains a complicated religious phenomenon. They
made themselves a נזיר nazir so that they could bring the קרבן
חטאת. korban chatas.
Anyway, כדי שיתחייב קרבן חטאת למקום. K'dei sheyischayeiv korban chatas l'Makom.
So that's why somebody became a
נזיר. nazir. That would be an example of a נדבה. nedava. Alright.
In a way it's sort of also hearkens to the idea of
נדבה nedava as a freely given קרבן, korban, right? Because then it
sort of ultimately relates to their ability to give this type of
a קרבן. korban. Okay. רבי שמעון אומר, Rabbi Shimon omer, רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon says, לא נדרו בנזיר, lo nadru b'nazir, אלא לא נדרו
בנזיר. ela lo nadru v'nazir. No, no, no,
they wouldn't do that. אלא הרוצה להביא עולה, Ela harotzeh l'havi olah,
here's what they would do. If a guy wanted to bring an
עולה, olah, מנדב ומביא. minadev umeivi.
You'd make a נדבה, nedava, not a נדר neder again, notice, a
נדבה. nedava. שלמים מנדב ומביא. Shlamim minadev umeivi. שלמים Shlamim
you can do that by a נדבה, nedava, free will. תודה וארבעה
מיני לחמה, Todah v'arba'ah minei lachmah, the תודה todah and the four
loaves of bread, מנדב
ומביא, minadev umeivi, you do a נדבה. nedava. אבל בנזירות לא התנדבו.
Aval binziros lo hisnadvu.
But even though they would נעבך nebach never be able to bring
a חטאת, chatas, they nevertheless would not make themselves into a נזיר.
nazir. Why not? כדי שלא יקראו חוטאים, K'dei shelo yikar'u chot'im, because
even if you haven't actually sinned, by a נזיר nazir you'll still
be called a sinner. שנאמר וכפר עליו מאשר חטא על הנפש. Shene'emar
v'chipper alav me'asher chata al hanefesh.
He will atone for him for that that he sinned against the
soul. Now the פסוקים psukim that actually relates to somebody who became
טמא, tamei, כי תהיה טמא לנפש. ki tihyeh tamei lanefesh. Okay, but
that is learned by at least from by here רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon to say that there's actually always a bad part of the
phenomenon of נזירות, neziros, I guess focusing on the fact that it
sort of like separates you out of society and you might be
doing it for a type of a יוהרא, yuhara, for a type
of a self-serving religious motivation, but the אשר חטא על הנפש. asher
chata al hanefesh. points out to the other part that gets emphasized
by the נזירות, nezirut, which is the asceticism aspect of it, and
that you actually are depriving yourself, you know, you can say you're
depriving yourself also of being a member of society, right? This is
actually because sort of denying yourself the normal types of parts of
an existence, which is the sort of societal, you know, being embedded
in society and being able to sort of have the pleasure from
this world, and therefore that's a way in which that is intrinsically
a negative religious phenomenon. You know, gets to the same question the
גמרא Gemara has about taking a תענית. taanis. Is somebody who's יושב
בתענית yoshev b'taanis נקרא חוטא nikra choteh or נקרא קדוש? nikra kadosh?
You know, which can get to a question of not just motivation,
but of a real profound religious question, right? How much do we
have the sense of this, you know, body-soul dualism, and the ideal
is to separate physically from this world and totally focus on God
and deny oneself of the physical pleasures, and any sort of, you
know, connection to this world is like a concession? You know, by
and large we sort of see that much more as a Christian
type of a religious idea, whereas Judaism is much more of an
embodied religion and we don't see ourselves like at war with the
physical world, okay, but you know, that is not all so black
and white. I mean, the רמב"ם Rambam in his פירוש משניות, Peirush
Mishnayos, you know, speaks at length and he says that the whole
approach of חסידי אשכנז Chasidei Ashkenaz of asceticism and self-denial, he basically
says they learned it all from the Christians. It's all like a
negative religious phenomenon. לא דייך מה שאסרה לך תורה, Lo dayecha mah
she'asra lacha Torah, you know,
and that that's just very unhealthy. But you know, we've always had
both of those impulses, and therefore you have this debate. Is being
in a תענית קדוש taanis kadosh or is being in a תענית
חוטא? taanis choteh? Is a נזיר קדוש nazir kadosh or is a
נזיר חוטא? nazir choteh? Okay. So ר' שמעון Reb Shimon says the
נזיר nazir is always an element, even regardless of motivation, there's always
this element that separating yourself from this world is a חוטא, choteh,
and therefore he says they would never accept it upon themselves, okay?
So we'll wrap this up tomorrow, but this interesting debate about the
real nature of these religious phenomena of נדר, neder, נזירות, nezirut, תענית,
taanis, and so on.